Guide to the Mary Sue Jones Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Mary Sue Jones Papers
1931-1992
1949-1992
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Jones, Mary Sue
SWWC.009a
14 Linear Feet
28 boxes
Mary Sue Jones' Papers span the years from 1931 to 1992 with most of the material dating from the 1960s through the 1980s. Contained here are class notes, scripts, set designs, costume designs, playbills, letters, photographs, records, audiotapes, reports, clippings, magazines, articles, awards, school records, yearbooks, scrapbooks, personal effects, and mementos.
Scope and Contents
Jones' papers are divided into two series: 1. Texas records; 2. New Mexico records. They span the years from 1931 to 1992 with most of the material dating from the 1960s through the 1980s. Contained here are class notes, scripts, set designs, costume designs, playbills, letters, photographs, records, audiotapes, reports, clippings, magazines, articles, awards, school records, yearbooks, scrapbooks, personal effects, and mementos. The Texas series contains three subseries: Education and Teaching; Acting, Design, and Directing; and Dallas Theater Center Administration.
The first subseries of the Texas files presents information on Jones' education at Baylor University and her teaching of acting and design at both Baylor and Trinity Universities. The second offers a good deal of information on her career as actor, director, and designer at the Dallas Theater Center. The third subseries covers her work as assistant artistic director to Paul Baker and is especially informative on the state of affairs during the transfer of the directorship at the Dallas Theater Center from Paul Baker to Adrian Hall.
The New Mexico series is arranged into four subseries: Teaching and Directing, Paul Baker Festival, Production and Script Files, and Personal. The first subseries provides information on Jones' work as artist-in-residence, and later as a faculty member at the College of Santa Fe. The second centers on the career of Paul Baker, especially at the Dallas Theater Center, and documents the 1990 festival organized by his former students to honor him. The third subseries is Jones' collection of scripts or production files including many of the plays performed at the Dallas Theater Center. The fourth contains material on Mary Sue's private life and non-theatrical interests, such as her baby book, gardening, and decoration ideas for her Santa Fe home.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
Donated by Diane and Don Malouf and the Birkhead family.
Biographical Notes
Actress, director, and designer Mary Sue Birkhead Fridge Jones was born on August 24, 1930 in Carthage, Missouri. She entered Baylor University in 1948 as an art student but eventually found her way to the Theater Department under Paul Baker. She received a Master's in Drama in 1955 from Baylor. Jones began student teaching in 1954 and became an integral part of the Paul Baker teaching team. She taught acting and design at Baylor and later followed Baker in his move to Trinity University, where she was an assistant professor.
Jones was present at the founding of the Dallas Theater Center in 1959 and was made assistant director of the facility. She starred in many Dallas Theater Center productions, winning Dallas's Billy Award in 1963 as best actress for her performance in Sister. Some of her other starring roles at the Dallas Theater Center were in The Taming of the Shrew, Medea, and A Streetcar Named Desire. She was costume and set designer for Julius Caesar, Journey to Jefferson, Macbeth and Marat-Sade to mention only a few. In the 1980s, Baker promoted Jones to associate artistic director and then co-artistic director. Baker, forced to resign from the Dallas Theater Center by the Board of Trustees in 1982, picked her as his successor. The Board appointed her interim artistic director until Adrian Hall was hired to fill the position in 1983. Jones then moved to Santa Fe as artist in residence at the College of Santa Fe, where she taught acting and directed at the Greer Garson Theater Center. In 1988, she was made a full time faculty member of the college.
Mary Sue Jones' first marriage was to Roy Fridge, an artist who also created posters for the Dallas Theater Center. She married Preston Jones on September 7, 1964. Mary Sue Jones died in Santa Fe June 27, 1992.
Related Materials
Preston Jones Papers (Collection 9) and the Paul and Kitty Baker Papers (Collection 35).
Related Materials
Books from the library of Preston and Mary Sue Jones have been cataloged and the records are searchable through the Alkek Library online catalog, http://catalog.library.txstate.edu
Index Terms
Subjects
Theater; Women musical theater producers and directors; Actresses; College theater -- Texas; Drama
Subjects (Persons)
Jones, Mary Sue; Jones, Preston, 1936-1979; Baker, Paul, 1911-2009
Subjects (Corporations)
Dallas Theater Center
- Texas records, 1949-1983, undated
  Series Description
  The first subseries, Education and Training, contains Mary Sue's yearbooks, class notes, and her thesis from her years at Baylor University, where she gained her undergraduate and masters degrees in drama. Also included are slides of the 1952 trip to Paris made by the Baylor Drama students with Paul Baker.
  The next subseries, Acting, Design, and Directing Career, contains records, audiotapes, photographs, slides, posters, letters, scripts, set designs and costume designs. The material documents Mary Sue's career as an actor, designer and director at Baylor University and at the Dallas Theater Center. There are photographs of her performances, recordings of Hamlet and her Speak 4 Trio group, and original drawings of her set and costume designs. There are also examples of her first husband Roy Fridge's art work, including the posters he designed for the Dallas Theater Center's productions, and some examples of the artwork of set designer Virgil Beavers.
  Mary Sue Jones had been with Paul Baker since the inception of the Dallas Theater Center and at the time of his forced retirement she was appointed interim artistic director. The third subseries, Dallas Theater Center Administration, contains administrative files from the executive committee and search committee as well as budgets, planning files, memos, clippings, correspondence, contracts, and playbills. Here is found good documentation of Mary Sue's stint as Interim Artistic Director in 1982, including her plans for the redirection of the theater, and clippings and memos relating to the search for the new director which resulted in the hiring of Adrian Hall.
  - Education and Teaching, 1949-1983, undated
    - Baylor University yearbook, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Baylor University yearbook, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Baylor University yearbook, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Class notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Baylor thesis, rough draft (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Note cards relating to thesis (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Copy of thesis (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Baylor Othello Notes, Experimental Summer, two notebooks (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Façade," music by William Walton, words by Edith Sitwell (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Class notes—Europe, map of Paris with handwritten notes (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Slides of a trip to Europe, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Acting Notes, 1953, 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Class notes, 1953, 1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Class notes, 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Class notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Class notes, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Class notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Class notes, 1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Articles on the creative process in The Journal of the American Association of University Women, Scientific American, and "The Creative Mind at Work," article by Paul Baker, 1954, 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Acting class syllabi, 1962, 1963, 1976, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Acting class syllabi, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Design class notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Dallas Theater Center material and notes, 1962-1963, 1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Notes, "The Polite World of the Eighteenth Century", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Notes, Henry V, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Notes and various Shakespeare scenes, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Acting class scenes, character analysis worksheet, 1979, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Class notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "Symbols" class material and articles, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "Symbols" class, assignments and notes, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Scholarship materials, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Readings and notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - Design class, syllabus, handouts, and notes, 1974-1975, 1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Design class, syllabus, handouts, and notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Directing class, student papers, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Directing class, student papers, 1983, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Acting, Design, and Directing Career, 1955-1973, undated
    - Hamlet recording, Speak 4 Trio script and reel-to-reel tapes of Impressions of Christmas, 1957, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - Speak 4 Trio cassette and reel-to-reel tapes, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Slides, Roy and Mary Sue Fridge, Roy Fridge's art, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Roy Fridge's art, watercolors, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Roy Fridge's art, watercolor and sketches, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Photos, Mary Sue Jones, Baylor and DTC, 1955-1969 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Photos, Mary Sue and Preston Jones, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Dallas Theater Center programs and informational pamphlets, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Posters, photos and slides, Mary Sue and Preston Jones in DTC productions, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Photos, Mary Sue Jones in DTC productions, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Sister, play by Glenn Allen Smith, script with handwritten notes, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
    - Correspondence with Mr. Harry Buckwitz, Director Staedtische Buehnen, Frankfurt Am Main, Germany concerning Caucasian Chalk Circle, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Slides of set and costume designs, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Set and costume designs, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Souvenir collection of costume designs for The Tempest, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Set designs, sketches and watercolors, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Photocopy of Hospitals of Paris, pages 69-91, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Notes on Seagull, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Scholarship Award for Creative Greatness, Mary Sue and Preston Jones, April 7, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Summer and Smoke directing notes, framed program, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Dallas Theater Center Administration, 1963-1983, undated
    - Dallas Theater Center Board and Executive committee, budget committee reports, correspondence, memos, award and scholarship information, and board meeting reports, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 6-9)
    - Dallas Theater Center Company, correspondence and operations information, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Copy of "Executive Summary," November 1977, and DTC "Report on Examinations of Financial Statements and Supplemental Data for the years ended August 31, 1977 and 1976," includes other relevant documents, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Trinity University position, includes search committee report, resumes, and correspondence, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - DTC Feasibility Study Report, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlets and letter from Audrey Wood to Hal Willis of Hal Willis Productions, 1977-1978, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Various committee reports, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Clippings and correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Clippings and correspondence, 1980, 1983 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - News stories about Jones' friends and acquaintances, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Actors and agents, list developed for production of War and Peace, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Directing class, syllabus and reading list, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Women in Theater, conference information, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Texas Foundation for Women's Resources, "Texas Women: A Celebration of History," Gala Opening, notes, programs, schedule of events, set designs, and script, May 9, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Mary Sue Jones personal file, correspondence and addresses, 1981-1983 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Al Milano projects, memos and clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Dallas Theater Center business, 1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - DTC crisis, clippings, articles, memos, and remarks by Paul Baker, Spring 1982 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Budget Information, 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
    - Lawyers, thank-you letters, business cards, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Congratulatory letters and cards, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Dallas and Theater Crafts magazines; Trinity University Graduate Bulletin, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Articles about Ed Herrmann, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Articles about Adrian Hall's selection as Paul Baker's successor, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Memos, photographs, and clippings relating to Adrian Hall, 1983, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Mary Sue Jones in Ladybug, Ladybug Fly Away Home, performed at the American College Theatre Festival, programs, correspondence, and clippings, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, requests for letters of recommendation, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Playbills, 1963-1983 (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
    - Articles, clippings, and information about other theaters, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Theater articles, clippings, information, research, 1982-1983 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Clippings and articles about Jones, the DTC, and teaching methods, 1982-1983 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Theater Communications Group national conference information folders, 1980, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Dallas Theater Center season, correspondence, schedules of events, budget information, press releases, newspaper articles, class schedules, memos, grant applications, and meeting minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 12, Folder 4-7)
    - DTC Employee Handbook, Copy of NEA Challenge Grant Proposal, memos, Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1983, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, clippings, Finance Committee agenda, photos, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Finance Committee documents, Jones' resume, budgets for shows, phone directory, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - DTC correspondence, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - New Students Guide, DTC Handbook, DTC Budget, 1981-1982 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Contracts, drafts, 1982-1983 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Speeches and correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Green Room chats, correspondence, notes, and articles, 1983, undated (Box 13, Folder 8-9)
    - Press release contacts, 1982-1983 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Interim Artistic Director, 1982-1983 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
    - Budget, 1982-1983 (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
- New Mexico records, 1931-1992, undated
  Mary Sue Jones left the Dallas Theater Center in 1983 and joined the College of Santa Fe as artist in residence. She taught and directed at the Greer Garson Theater Center becoming a full time faculty member at the College of Santa Fe in 1988. The first subseries, Teaching and Directing, contains class notes, student theses, reviews of College productions, and notes on faculty and college administration. Besides her own theater work, Mary Sue continued to manage the rights to Preston's plays and to promote his memory and the production of his works. In this series, there are clippings about Preston as well as material on the Dallas Theater Center Endowment Fund set up in his memory.
  Mary Sue Jones met Paul Baker as a student at Baylor University, and she went on to work closely with him as a member of his core group of artist-teachers until his forced retirement from the Dallas Theater Center in 1982. Afterwards, she continued to keep in touch with her mentor, inviting him to Santa Fe to oversee a production of Preston Jones' The Last Meeting of the Knights of the White Magnolia in 1985, while at the same time organizing a tribute to him. She also took a prominent part in the 1990 Paul Baker festival in Waco, "Second Harvest." The second subseries, Paul Baker Festival Files, contains newspaper clippings, programs, and letters, much of which focuses on Baker's career and theatrical influence.
  The next subseries, Script and Production Files, contains Mary Sue's collection of scripts, articles and research material on stage productions. Many of the scripts are annotated with remarks on interpretation and stage directions. A good number of these plays were performed at the Dallas Theater Center. They are arranged alphabetically by title.
  The final subseries, entitled Personal, presents aspects of Mary Sue's life from her birth in Carthage, Missouri, through her marriage to and divorce from the sculptor Roy Barto Fridge, her life with Preston at the Dallas Theater Center, her widowhood in Santa Fe, to her death in 1992. Present are her baby book, school records, divorce papers, awards, photographs, letters, clippings, and notices on her death. Her clippings files contain information on matters that were of particular interest to her, such as gardening, the Dallas Theater Center, Preston Jones, home decoration, birds and wildlife, etc.
  - Teaching and Directing, 1982-1992, undated
    - Clippings, playbills, photos, 1982-1986 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Greer Garson Theater Center Department of Performing Arts student handbook, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Sanderson, Barb, "Professional Theatre Graduate Programs: The Students' Eye View," Masters Thesis, August 7, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Hofland, John, "Relating Right Brain Research to the Design Process," Masters Thesis, August 7, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Clippings, research, photos, 1984-1985, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Dallas Theater Center Endowment Fund, 1986-1987 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Acting class notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Performing Class notes, Notebook I, Fall 1984 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Performing Class Notes, Notebook II, Fall 1984 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Acting IV, class notes, Fall 1986 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Acting class notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Performance Studies/ Acting IV, class notes, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Performance Studies/ Acting IV, class notes, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Acting I and Audition notes, Spring 1988 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Acting I and Playwriting, Spring 1989 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Class notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Performance Studies/Acting IV, class notes, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Class notes, undated (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
    - Speech/ Performance Studies, class notes, Notebook II, Fall 1984 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Acting I and Playwriting, class notes, Spring 1987 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Mary Sue Jones' notes and observations about Performance Studies Class, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Auditions Training, Spring 1990 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Performance Studies/ Acting IV, Fall 1990 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Resume information, school memos, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Acting I and Playwriting, Spring 1991 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Acting class notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Performance Studies, class notes, Fall 1991 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Performance Studies, class notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Performance Studies, final scenes, video, Fall 1991 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Performing Arts Faculty, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Paul Baker Festival Files, 1983-1986, 1990-1991
    - Clippings, Dallas Theater Center, Paul Baker, and Adrian Hall, 1983-1986 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Paul Baker Festival mailing list, February 27, 1990 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Second Harvest, Paul Baker Festival, clippings, correspondence, maps, speeches, articles, August 1990 (Box 19, Folder 5-6)
    - The Paul Baker Theater: A Photo History, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Script and Production Files, 1977, 1980, 1987, undated
    - And a Nightingale Sang, by Cecil P. Taylor, script and prop list (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - As I Lay Dying, by William Faulkner, adapted for Baylor Theater production by Robert L. Flynn (Preston Jones' copy) (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - A Bug in Her Ear (La Puce A L'oreille), by Georges Feydeau, tr. G. B. Shaw (Preston Jones' copy) (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Children of a Lesser God, by Mark Medoff, last revision, June 13, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - The Crucible, by Arthur Miller, script, background information, and notes (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
    - Curious in LA, by Glenn Allen Smith (Preston Jones' copy) (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - A Different Drummer, Gene McKinney (Preston Jones' copy) (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - The Dining Room, by A.R. Gurney, Jr. (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Door Play, by Sallie Baker Laurie, 1977 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Door Play, by Sallie Baker Laurie, script with handwritten notes (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - The Dresser, by Ronald Harwood, script and notes (Box 21, Folder 5-7)
    - Firekeeper, by Mark Medoff (Preston Jones' copy) (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Fuse, by Sally Netzel (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Hamlet, by William Shakespeare (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Hamlet, by William Shakespeare, as arranged by Paul Baker and staff (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Hay Fever, by Noel Coward (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - A Home Away From, by Glenn Allen Smith (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - The House of Bernarda Alba, by Federico Garcia Lorca, maps, notes, and research (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - The House of Bernarda Alba, by Federico Garcia Lorca, script (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - House of Blue Leaves, by John Guare, script and notes (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - House of Blue Leaves, by John Guare, script (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Importance of Being Ernest, by Oscar Wilde, script and notes (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Importance of Being Ernest, by Oscar Wilde, thank- you cards, notes, and research (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Jack Ruby, All American, by Paul Baker & John Logan (Preston Jones' copy) (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Journey to Jefferson, a staged dramatization of William Faulkner's As I Lay Dying adapted by Robert L. Flynn, scripts (Box 23, Folder 6-9)
    - LuAnn Hampton Laverty Oberlander, by Preston Jones, script and notes (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Our Town, by Thorton Wilder, script and notes (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Our Town, by Thorton Wilder, notes (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - A Man for All Seasons, by Robert Bolt, script, notes, and research (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - A Man for All Seasons, by Robert Bolt, script (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Of Time and the River, by Tom Wolfe, adapted by Baylor Theater (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Picnic, by William Inge, script, notes, and research (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Puppet Makers, by Norman D. Schultz (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Sam: A Play Based on the Life and Imagination of Mark Twain, by Sally Netzel (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Sadie's Kitchen, by Bonnie Beardsley, script and correspondence with the author, 1987 (Box 25, Folder 3-4)
    - Sister, by Glenn Allen Smith (Preston Jones' copy) (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Sister, by Glenn Allen Smith (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Summer and Smoke, by Tennessee Williams (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Summer and Smoke, by Tennessee Williams, script, notes and research (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Writes and Wrongs, John Francis, public television program, August 1987 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Personal, 1931-1992, undated
    - Baby book and National Honor Society membership card, 1931-1941, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)